All right, everybody.
Next, I would like to welcome
Deanie Gregory to present.
So Deanie,
I will give you the floor. Okay.
So my paper is entitled
Archival storytelling.
And it's it comes from my current book
project by the same title.
And the subtitle refers
to a portion of chapter two.
I'm Dean Gregory
from the Electronic Literature
Lab at Washington State University
in Vancouver, Washington.
Not the beautiful Canada. Vancouver.
Okay, so what you're looking at
are two unassuming artifacts.
The one on the left
is a digitized booklet.
It was paper to start with.
It's been digitized
30 pages in length and a printed booklet.
I'm still holding
32 pages of photocopied content
between two pieces of gray paper
bound by two staples.
And we can see by looking at these
at the digitized booklet is titled Cyber
Writing Selected Resources
for Right Internet Resources for writers,
and the author's name.
Simon Mills appears in the center
in the black background
in the middle of the page.
The printed booklet is titled Trace
Selected Internet Resources
for writers and subtitled formerly
The Cyber Writing Project.
Mills's name
appears at the bottom left of the cover.
So these artifacts are
part of the archives of the Trace Online
Writing Center,
which was the influential digital
writing community founded by Sue Thomas
at Nottingham Trent University in the UK
and active for well over a decade.
And they were donated over the years
by by Thomas and by Helen Whitehead,
who served as the manager of education
and training at the Trace Online
Writing School.
The digitized booklet
is included in the Trace Digital Archives
on the yellow server.
The printed booklet has been stored
among many other physical artifacts
belonging to trace,
and you can see here box 24
of the Electronic Literature
Organization's archives.
Both of these are managed by my lab
at Washington State University, Vancouver.
But what exactly are these artifacts?
What stories do they tell
and why do they matter to us today?
I'm going to answer that question for you.
So answering those questions shares
light on the origins
of an international community
that influenced
ELO and other international arts
organizations.
One that showed us how to forge
deep relationships across great distances
through the use of digital technologies.
They pioneered the stuff
we're kind of doing today, right?
One that showed us
what digital writing could be
and how to effectively promote it,
and one that launched and nurtured
the careers of many, many born
digital scholars and artists worldwide,
some of whom are here at this conference.
This paper starts at the premise
that archives tell stories.
They tell tales
about the early days of the field.
They document the artist who pioneered
experimental forms and the efforts artists
took to promote them.
They show us the technologies
used for production and then disappeared
into obsolescence, as well as a hardware,
software and removable discs that failed.
And the viruses and glitches artists
reviled within leverage
in the creation of their art.
And I'm going to call that Dena Larson
here in The Green Bug.
They trace the shifting views
towards and forms
and the publishing houses and the journals
and the galleries and museums
and the organizations
that provided support.
They help us remember the communities,
the communities of practice like trace
that rose into prominence,
and the immense work that it takes
to keep board
digital media accessible to the public.
At the heart of this presentation
is the desire to encourage us to rethink
the role of archives
or born digital literature, art and games
not as old things of a bygone era
that do not matter for the present
or the future, but rather something
we must rely on for telling our stories,
for preserving our law
and ensuring our history.
Without the stories that archives tell,
there is no field.
And Kate
Hill said that outright at the event
that I held just about two months ago.
We know from reading
traces account of its history,
as recorded in the program for incubation
2000 conference,
and in the introduction to Traces
of Commemoration of ten Years
of Artistic innovation at Trace.
1995 is given as the year trace began.
Traces of the Trace Online Writing Center,
written by artisan scholar J.R.
Carpenter, also lists 95 as a year
that trace was started,
but these two artifacts suggest
a more nuanced understanding of the year
trace was founded,
revealing the evolution of an idea
that the web could be leveraged
for digital writing to its implementation
that resulted in the creation
of trace.
An introduction
to the Frame Journal of Culture
and Technology, and this is located
in the next at the Frame collection.
Sue Thomas tells us that after
she was awarded funding from the English
department in May of 95, Mills
did the research for the Cyber
Writing project for her during the summer
as a student tutored in fiction
writing in the new graduate program
in Creative Writing at Nottingham Trent.
The document took shape as a list
of websites, with brief descriptions
and URL that followed in the style of Alan
Lewis voice of the shuttle,
and some of us might remember that handout
now a website all text
they all network of art and technology.
Mills's output
led Thomas to realize that cyberspace
was teeming, quote unquote,
with people who wanted to explore the web
as a space for production, consumption
and consumption and exchange of writing.
To put the cyber
writing project in context is 30 pages
are indeed teeming with yours for journals
and zines, sites
for poetry and fiction, online
resources and virtual communities
and moves and MUDs and meshes.
Some of us might remember
those communities.
1995 was early days of the web,
with Netscape featured prominently
in both project booklets, just released
in December of 94 and driving the.com
boom by the summer of 95,
when Mills was working on the project.
It's estimated that less than ten
less than 1000 web
servers were in operation at that time
globally.
Lose voice of the shuttle, published
originally 94, had by 99 grow to 70 pages.
So Mills's research for Thomas,
compiled in 30 pages
and 95, was like loose,
pretty far thinking and timely.
But what is the document?
Trace
selected internet resources for writers,
and what is its relationship
to the Cyber Writing Project?
As mentioned previously, trace
selected internet
resources for writers
is 32 pages of photocopied content
and subtitled formerly
the Cyber Writing Research Project,
suggesting that it followed
after the publication of Cyber Writing.
If we open up the cyber writing booklet
and I'm having this,
these are the two pages
of the two different versions.
We see that it's updated,
but a statement about the information
was current as of as of September 95th,
which establishes an approximate timeframe
for the publication of that document.
Looking at the contents of the trace
booklet, we see that same statement about
September 95th, but as already stressed,
we can assume that the printed booklet
was published after the digital booklet
after the one that's digitalized.
Since it references on this cover,
cyber Writing project is formally.
Additionally,
the printed booklet references.
References
trace in the title on its cover, a name
that does not appear at all
in the digitized booklet.
Cyber writing is touted on the contents
page as a first fruit of cyber writing.
Entered research project
into writing on the internet
in the Department of English
and Media Studies at the University.
The printed booklet instead is listed
as the first route of trace
into use research project
into writing on the on the internet,
in the department, blah blah blah.
This change in the title of printed
booklet is telling Thomas herself notes
in the Brief History of the trace online
writing community that by 96,
when she and Mills
were planning the website, the name
cyber and cyber writing
had already become passé.
They arrived at the name of trace
with a capital A, which was a typo
that Mills made in an email to Thomas
that they just decided to stick with.
Besides a different project names, though,
the cover art helps to really timestamp
the two parties facts.
Some of us might remember this
wonderful tool
that we used to play
with the cover of Cyber writing.
It speaks experimentation
that desktop publishing made possible.
The cover was made with Mac paint.
Some of us might remember that
that was the bitmap editor software
bundled on the Macintosh computer
and supported by Apple until 95.
Its title made with the pencil tool,
and I used to sit and play.
In fact, I still do on my own Macintoshes.
And then the the background
with the pattern tool.
The second artifact is missing
this inventive design
from its cover art, showing the title
instead in a more traditional typeface.
While the difference
between the visual presentation
of the two artifacts
could have been impacted
by the upgrade to the Macintosh
operating system that affected Mac
paint after 95, it could also be due
to the difference in their purpose.
The former was produced
as a report for an academic department,
while the latter could be used
for a wider dissemination to organizations
expecting a more conventional
approach to reports.
The content of the two articles
also helps to timestamp them.
The minor and minor difference
in pagination
results in two additional pages
in the printed booklet.
Additionally,
two sites were added to the two journals
and zines in the printed booklet
Freak and Speed, the former
a digital underground community
located in the UK, and the latter
the first edition of a
theoretical journal.
The poetry section of the Cyber
Writing Project, included
the entry for Asian Poets,
which is omitted in the printed booklet.
These are small changes that don't
necessarily help to date the project,
but it shows the kind of changes
that were already taking place online,
which I think is pretty cool.
But let me go back.
But the cool thing is
the addition of items to the searching
the World Wide Web in the printed booklet
precisely dates that booklet
this technology company was pioneered.
They pioneered the traffic server
for the web, was founded in January of 96
by UC Berkeley's Eric Brewer
and his student, Paul Gauthier.
So the printed booklet follows
about a year after the production of Cyber
Writing booklet, constituting it as
a second edition of Cyber Writing Project.
Tending is kind of fun.
One other piece of
evidence that I find useful
is the announcement on this contact page
that the project and the booklet,
and this is a booklet that that of the
booklet will soon be available online
in a clickable format.
They don't call it a website,
they call it a clickable format.
As Thomas reports, it's clear
after cyber writing had been produced
it needed to be online, which led Mills
to teach himself how to code. In
a few months later,
the first trace website was complete
with a quote,
a large version of Cyber Writing List,
which launched at the Virtual Futures
Conference at Warwick
University in England in May 96th.
We can assume that this enlarged version
is referencing
the trace booklet.
The origin stories of the two artifacts
tell us
is this in the summer of 95, when Mills
was commissioned to conduct his research
of writing resources on the internet
and on through May 96th,
when the second edition was released
and the website announced
that the virtual Features conference,
Thomas had shifted her thinking from cyber
writing to trace, having collected
enough data from the research published
in the two booklets to prepare materials
for seeking financial support.
Thomas
in August of 97, proposed and received
365,000 pounds
from the Literature Department of the Arts
Council of England to, quote, establish
an international online writing community,
which ultimately shifted the Trace project
to the Trace Online Writing Center.
So, to answer the questions posed at the
start of this paper, these two artifacts
constitute the founding documents
of this important community.
They show that what began as a research
about digital writing resources on the web
carried with it
the kernel of a vision of a digital
writing community that would go on
to promote the web for communicating,
sharing ideas, publishing
works, and advancing digital writing.
What we should also find interesting
is that together, the two booklets
document how one can go about building
an organization.
The first steps
Thomas took to gain support,
and the relationship between research
and practice and academic settings.
We see much of the same efforts used by
Yellow's founders and early board members
to create our community. Here.
I'm going to wrap up here by saying Mills
research undertaken for Thomas collected
information that determined
the viability of digital writing,
a project from which many have benefited.
As such, they document the cyber
Writing Project, the transition from cyber
writing to trace the shift
from photocopied booklet
to a web based resource,
the emergence of one of the earliest
online writing communities,
and material evidence of how writers
and scholars
navigated the pre web search web internet.
Lastly, they also
represent a broader,
largely forgotten of print
born web directories
that includes Lose Voice of the shuttle.
And here's an example of his web
and others mentioned in this paper,
which in their early states, were shared
as stapled together
booklets
before they appeared online on the web.
It can be a nice dissertation topic
for somebody in some with this paper.
Broadly proposes
is that archives are narrative systems.
The field of electronic literature
is inherently archival,
and archives are essential
to the field itself.
Without our archives,
which our announcement cards
websites captured by the way, back
machine research reports, blah blah blah
and other forms of output.
There is no field,
and in the end, there can be no community
or evidence that whenever even existed.
Thank you.